Nathanael Greene Papers 1777-1780 Mss.B.G83
American Philosophical Society
- Series I: Correspondence, 1777-1780; 3 lin. feet
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 7; 2pp.; Morgan, Jacob (Box 4)
    Reading - Same as letter above, with the exception of a postscript relative to the return of stores for the month of March.
    vii, 45
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 28; 2pp.; Morgan, Jacob (Box 4)
    Reading - Account of horses and teams furnished to Col. Cox and those ready to start.
    v, 87
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 29; 1p.; Morgan, Jacob (Box 4)
    Reading - Report of wagons and horses in his brigade.
    v, 93
  - to John Cox, 1779 May 30; 1p.; Morgan, Jacob (Box 4)
    Reading - Acknowledging favor of 27th inst. Report of stores forwarded. Conflicting orders.
    v, 98
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 13; 1p.; Morgan, Jacob (Box 4)
    Smith's Tavern - Acknowledging favor of 5th inst. Has no information concerning the arrival of the horses and teams. Necessity of sending punctual returns.
    vi, 57
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 9; 2pp.; Morgan, Jacob (Box 4)
    Reading - Sends by bearer eleven good teams, laden with fifty-five barrels of flour. Impossible to enlist carters except by the day, at $ 10.00 per day. Wagons Col. Cox ordered almost ready. Axes and camp kettles on hand.
    i 102
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 January 29; 2pp.; Morgan, Jacob (Box 4)
    Reading - Being a calculation of debts due on account of the quartermaster and forage departments, but not absolutely exact, as there are some accounts against the department not yet found.
    i, 104
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 February 4; 2pp.; Morgan, Jacob (Box 4)
    Reading - Acknowledging favor of the 19th and observing by it that accounts of outstanding debts are to be rendered by March 1. Will do his best, but owing to the snow thinks it unlikely he can collect the whole by that time.
    i, 103
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 January 30; 1p.; Morgan, John (Box 4)
    Philadelphia - Asking his assistance in procuring him quarters for attending the court-martial at Dr. Shippen's approaching trial. Presumes to trouble Gen. Greene with this application on account of politeness shown him by the General when last in camp.
    i, 101
  - to Charles Pettit, 1779 May 1; 1p.; Morris, Gouverneur, 1752-1816 (Box 4)
    Philadelphia - Desires that harmony and good understanding may be cultivated between the public servants and the government of South Carolina; has no doubt the President of that State has good reasons for detaining vessels mentioned in Mr. Livingston's letter. Directions concerning these vessels, which are to be loaded with rice. Urges prompt obedience on Mr. Livingston's part to directions which may be given to him.
    vii, 17
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 19; 1p.; Morris, Gouverneur, 1752-1816 (Box 4)
    Philadelphia - Asking that, if it is proper and convenient, his nephew, Lewis Morris, may be taken into Gen. Greene's family as a volunteer aide.
    v, 29
  - to Clement Biddle, 1779 July 26; 1p.; Morris, Lewis (Box 4)
    West Point - Requested by Gen. Greene to ask for a return of al such officers as are employed in the forage department.
    ix, 83
  - to Charles Beatty, 1779 September 3; 1p.; Morris, Lewis (Box 4)
    West Point - Directed by Gen. Greene to acknowledge receipt of his favor of the 21st July, together with the enclosed returns.
    ix, 84
  - to George Gray, 1779 April 5; 1p.; Moxley, Rhodom (Box 4)
    Order to repair the bearer's gun-lock.
    xii, 71
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 11; 1p.; Moylan, John (Box 4)
    Newburgh - Desiring him to send a receipt, endorsed, for a hat which will be delivered by bearer.
    i, 105
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 5; 2pp.; Moylan, Stephen, 1737-1811 (Box 4)
    North Castle - If Mr. Bennett, bearer of this, fails to get money from Col. Bostick to pay for the forage of the Light Dragoons, he begs Gen. Greene to supply him with $ 20,000, as his honor is engaged that the inhabitants shall be duly paid for their forage.
    i, 106
  - to Nehemiah Hubbard, 1780 January 6, 30; 2pp.; Moylan, Stephen, 1737-1811 (Box 4)
    Middletown - Requesting him to settle Messrs. Hall and Co.'s accounts.
    ix, 69, 69a
  - to Superintendent of Artificers, 1779 April 2; 1p.; Muhlenberg, Peter (Box 4)
    Asking to have his horse well shod, as he is going on a journey.
    i, 110
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 11; 1p.; Muhlenberg, Peter (Box 4)
    Asking that the bearer, James Dunn, a ropemaker, may be given work in Gen. Greene's department.
    vii, 67
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 27; 1p.; Murfree, Hardy (Box 4)
    Paramus - Asking permission to purchase a horse belonging to the public.
    i, 111
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 11; 1p.; Murray, John (Box 4)
    Boston - Begging him to forward to Capt. Sargent certain letters from his family. Hopes to see him before summer is over.
    vii, 75
  - to George Gray, 1778 October 4; 1p.; Nevill, John (Box 4)
    xii, 108
  - to George Gray, 1778 December 14; 1p.; Nevill, John (Box 4)
    Order to shoe his horse and charge it to his account.
    xii, 83
  - to Robert Lettis Hooper, 1779 May 14; 3pp.; Okley, J. (Box 4)
    Bath - Giving information concerning a Mr. Smith, a captain in the Austrian service, and at one time in the service of the United States; also concerning two French gentlemen, his friends. Thinks there may be no reason for surmises of an evil tendency, but knows that very few foreign officers, who have left the American service in disgust or otherwise, are to be depended upon.
    v, 14
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 January 2; 2pp.; Olney, George (Box 4)
    Providence - Stating the salary which he will accept as Auditor of Accounts, to live in Gen. Greene's family and have equal privileges with the other officers in the department.
    i, 113
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 31; 2pp.; Olney, George (Box 4)
    Providence - Made application to Col. Angell to obtain permission for Capt. Littlefield to go and live with Gen. Greene during the present campaign. Account of his journey after leaving camp and his meeting with Mrs. Olney. Report that a French fleet will arrive in three weeks. Another expedition in preparation against Rhode Island.
    vi, 19
  - Circular letter to Deputies, 1779 July 15; 1p.; Olney, George (Box 4)
    Smith's Clove - Gen. Greene's orders that no wagoner returning from camp shall be paid any money without a special order from the Quartermaster-General's office.
    i, 112
  - to William Blodget, 1779 September 17; 1p.; Olney, George (Box 4)
    West Point - Requested by Gen. Greene to write and ask him about a sulky which was lent him in June, 1778. Col. Geo. Gibson, having made a demand on Gen. Greene for the value, he wishes to know the particulars of the matter.
    ix, 92
  - to Thomas Chase, 1779 September 18; 1p.; Olney, George (Box 4)
    West Point - Requested by Gen. Greene to acknowledge his favor of August 9, enclosing statement of accounts for one year. In case his conduct in Quartermaster's department should be examined into, agreeable to resolve of Congress, he will immediately transmit the result of their inquiry, be it favorable or unfavorable to his wishes.
    iii, 87
  - to Ephraim Bowen, 1779 November 15; 1p.; Olney, George (Box 4)
    West Point - Directed by Gen. Greene to tell him that if the tents are sent on early in the spring, it will answer. Advice concerning destination of hay and blankets. Army will probably march for winter quarters near Basking Ridge, November 17; Mrs. Greene, Mrs. Olney and the writer will set out then for Morristown.
    viii, 72
  - to Robert Lettis Hooper, 1779 November 15; 1p.; Olney, George (Box 4)
    West Point - Directed by Gen. Greene to acknowledge his favor of 12th inst., to express his pleasure with the readiness of the people to serve the public, and to ask him to put a stop to all preparations for the expected expeditions against New York.
    ix, 93
  - to Otis and Henley, 1779 November 15; 1p.; Olney, George (Box 4)
    West Point - Acknowledging in Gen. Greene's name the favors of 28th ult. and 2d inst. There being no immediate need for the tents, asks him to fill the orders more at his leisure, thereby decreasing the public expense.
    viii, 73
  - to John Mitchell, 1779 November 29; 1p.; Olney, George (Box 4)
    Morristown - Acknowledging in Gen. Greene's name the favor of 22d isnt., and thanking him for the sugar and tea. Informs him that Col. Cox and Col. Pettit will do everything to furnish him with money. Gen. Greene constantly engaged in fixing upon the ground to hut the army. When this is settled he will make a full representation to Congress of the department's distresses, and demand relief. Gives him leave to keep Capt. Sadler's company of artificers.
    viii, 74
  - to Udny Hay, n.d.; 1p.; Olney, George (Box 4)
    [no letter, just cover]
    xi, 8a
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 January 10; 2pp.; Otis, Samuel Allyne, 1740-1814 (Box 4)
    Boston - Informing him of the death of his partner, Mr. Andrews, who was shot by the accidental discharge of a pistol. Loss to the community. Will excuse the business now devolving upon him in the best manner possible.
    i, 108
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 January 10; 3pp.; Otis, Samuel Allyne, 1740-1814 (Box 4)
    Copy of the above letter.
    ix, 85
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 January 14; 3pp.; Otis, Samuel Allyne, 1740-1814 (Box 4)
    Boston - Acknowledging favor of 20th ult. Concerning the purchase of duck and other articles. Everything intolerably dear and also upon the rise. Makes certain suggestions for procuring supplies.
    ix, 85a
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 January 18; 2pp.; Otis, Samuel Allyne, 1740-1814 (Box 4)
    Boston - Has taken upon himself to execute the orders contained in Gen. Greene's letter of the 5th to his deceased friend. Can procure no vessels upon the terms offered by Congress. Mr. Lewis presses hard for a supply of money.
    viii, 77
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 3; 2pp.; Otis, Samuel Allyne, 1740-1814 (Box 4)
    Boston - Impossible to get the rice freighted unless Gen. Greene will give one-half or one-third and insure. Has made considerable purchases, in which he must have immediate monetary assistance.
    ix, 86
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 6; 3pp.; Otis, Samuel Allyne, 1740-1814 (Box 4)
    Boston - Setting forth what he has done as regards procuring vessels. Credit and cash both gone at present. Owners of vessels no opulent, so that cash must be advanced to get them to sea; also to get a supply of duck. Sends two silver cups by bearer, which Mr. Andrews bespoke before his death. Has lost within a few weeks his father, friend and wife. Advises putting a few stores on each vessel.
    iv, 74
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 10; 2pp.; Otis, Samuel Allyne, 1740-1814 (Box 4)
    Boston - Acknowledging receipt of$ 44,000 by Adams. Names of vessels, time of sailing and term on which they are hired. Loss of money if they are detained.
    iv, 73
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 11; 2pp.; Otis, Samuel Allyne, 1740-1814 (Box 4)
    Boston - Exact copy of preceding letter.
    iv, 72
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 11; 2pp.; Otis, Samuel Allyne, 1740-1814 (Box 4)
    Boston - Question of insuring the vessels hired. Marine Board has given Major Chase all the duck they can spare upon his application in Gen. Greene's name, leaving non for him [Otis]. Enclosing list of vessels.
    iv, 71
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 17; 2pp.; Otis, Samuel Allyne, 1740-1814 (Box 4)
    Boston - Announcing the arrival of various vessels with rice. Continued demands on him will render his situation very uncomfortable with out Gen. Greene's attention.
    v, 4
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 17; 2pp.; Otis, Samuel Allyne, 1740-1814 (Box 4)
    Announcing arrival of the brigantine Laurana with supply of rice. Mr. Livingston drawing upon him for certain expenses. [On back of MSS.] A bill of Otis and Henley's.
    v, 5
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 21, 22; 3pp.; Otis, Samuel Allyne, 1740-1814 (Box 4)
    Boston - Sending him two of the best pipes of wine he could meet with; the articles scarce and dear. Postscript - Stating the estimate relative to the rice. Wishes the escorts might be enjoined secrecy; every sum brought forward is magnified to millions. A fine prize brought in of 150 pipes of wine.
    v, 53, 53a
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 22; 4pp.; Otis, Samuel Allyne, 1740-1814 (Box 4)
    Boston - Capt. Collier's arrival with about 200 casks of rice, having encountered no setbacks. Will endeavor to negotiate some bills, but hopes that will not prevent his sending some cash. Mr. Livingston had no reason to complain; he had letters of advice sufficient to point out his duty, namely, to load the vessels with rice. Will exhibit his contracts to Gen. Greene and to Mr. Livingston if required.
    v, 58
  - to George Olney, 1779 October 9; 2pp.; Otis, Samuel Allyne, 1740-1814 (Box 4)
    Boston - No China cups and saucers to be had at present; will procure the first decent set in his power. Distresses caused by the Regulating Act. Hard to starve in a land of plenty, by the rascality of a people patriotic only in word. "High time to put an end to the war and reform manners."
    iii, 94
  - to Nathanael Greene, n.d.; 1p.; Otis, Samuel Allyne, 1740-1814 (Box 4)
    List of vessels taken up. [Enclosed in letter from Otis to Greene]. [NOTE: check, listed in Series IV]
    iv,70
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 January 1; 1p.; Otis and Andrews (Box 4)
    Boston - Have sent by Mr. Lawrence a book containing the year's account with the cloathier-general. Asks that it be forwarded.
    viii, 75
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 27; 1p.; Otis and Andrews (Box 4)
    Boston - the quarter cask of red port and dishes shall send at first opportunity care of Col. Smith. Some omissions and errors in the account, given you when here, which we have since corrected; and shall send you the after accounts in a few days.
    viii, 76
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 10; 2pp.; Otis and Henley (Box 4)
    Boston - Enclosing copy of protest of the captain of the Friendship, which was taken as a transport for rice and sustained damages. The Friendship apprized by indifferent men at £4500.
    vii, 64
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 10; 1p.; Otis and Henley (Box 4)
    A statement by Robert Craige, captain of the Friendship, sworn to before a Notary Public, protesting against the seizure and loss of his vessel by the ship Unicorn.
    vii, 64a
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 12; 2pp.; Otis and Henley (Box 4)
    Boston - Announcing the arrival of Capt. Bunker in port with 358 casks of rice. Six vessels laden likewise, sailed with him, some of which may be hourly expected. Asks for his immediate support to pay the freight. Having no orders for the disposition of the rice, delivered the cargo tot he issuing commissary.
    vii, 79
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 13; 1p.; Otis and Henley (Box 4)
    Boston - Informing him that certain casks were sent to Morgan Lewis by mistake instead of to Fishkill; therefore Col. Lewis must be held accountable.
    vii, 92
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 31; 1p.; Otis and Henley (Box 4)
    Boston - Fifteen marquees ordered are in hand. Encloses return of their doings for month of May.
    vi, 21
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 11; 2pp.; Otis and Henley (Box 4)
    Smith's Tavern in the Clove - Acknowledging favors of 10th, 12th, 13th, 17th, 21st, and 22d of May. Hears with mixture of pleasure and pain of the arrival of part of the rice and the loss of a part of the vessels. Promises to importune the Board of Treasury unceasingly. Difficulty of procuring proper supplies of cash. Mistaken policy of Congress has brought the currency into a most disagreeable situation. Much obliged for the wine purchased for the General.
    vi, 43
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 28; 2pp.; Otis and Henley (Box 4)
    New Windsor - Acknowledging favor of 12th inst. Number of suits woolen will make. No doubt of Southern news being authentic. Gen. Sullivan pushing into the Indian country. - "the savages may expect to feel the resentment of injured Americans. The blood of the innocent cries for vengeance." As soon as the British receive reinforcements at New York, "the scene will open."
    vi, 91
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 2; 1p.; Otis and Henley (Box 4)
    Boston - Question of purchasing duck for tents; very scarce and very dear. Recommends an application to the Commercial Committee.
    iii, 86
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 9; 1p.; Otis and Henley (Box 4)
    Boston - Assuring him that his requisition for tents and oakum shall be complied with as fast as possible. Congratulating him on Count d'Estaing's arrival.
    iii, 93
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 11; 1p.; Otis and Henley (Box 4)
    Boston - Presenting certain bills for payment, the sum being $ 100,000. Hopes this will not retard supply of cash promised by escort.
    i, 109
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 13; 2pp.; Otis and Henley (Box 4)
    Boston - Number of blankets and tents purchased. Could buy to more advantage had they earlier notice and, above all, a little cash.
    i, 107
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 27; 2pp.; Otis and Henley (Box 4)
    Boston - Acknowledging favor of 21st inst. Number of tents ready. Numerous creditors prevent further purchase. An order upon Nathaniel Appleton, Esq., might help the service.
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 28; 1p.; Otis and Henley (Box 4)
    Boston - Enclosing invoice of twelve hogsheads of tents and three casks of nails, to be forwarded immediately.
    viii, 79
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 2; 1p.; Otis and Henley (Box 4)
    Boston - Enclosing Mr. Livingston's account.
    ix, 89
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 12; 1p.; Otis and Henley (Box 4)
    Boston - Has sent to Col. Smith at Springfield, to be forwarded to Gen. Greene, thirteen hogsheads of tents and two hogsheads of woolens.
    viii, 80
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 14; 1p.; Otis and Henley (Box 4)
    Boston - Acknowledging cash. Necessity of procuring materials for tents. Hon. Messrs. Adams and Nana sail that morning for France.
    viii, 81
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 17; 1p.; Otis and Henley (Box 4)
    Boston - Announcing the dispatch by Mr. King of casks of tents, etc.
    ix, 90
  - to George Olney, 1779 November 24; 1p.; Otis and Henley (Box 4)
    Boston - In receipt of his letter countermanding the tents. Amount of money needed for past and present disbursements. Alas, for the fate of the Southern army; the gallant d'Estaing again baffled; "these reflections hang like a millstone."
    ix, 91
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 December 3; 1p.; Otis and Henley (Box 4)
    Boston - Enclosing invoice of tents and clothing, etc.
    i, 116
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 December 14; 2pp.; Otis and Henley (Box 4)
    Boston - Sorry every letter groans for remittance, but it can't be helped. Question of tents. Requisition from His Excellency for 1000 to 1500 tents; order confused with his [Gen. Greene's], but no harm done.
    iii, 95
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 February 19; 1p.; Otis and Henley (Box 4)
    Boston - Has forwarded to Col. Smith two hogsheads of markees; encloses invoice.
    i, 115
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1780 February 8; 1p.; Paine, Nathaniel (Box 5)
    Boston - Announcing a number of articles sent forward.
    i, 114
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 January 31; 1p.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809 (Box 5)
    Has stayed at home to avoid being asked questions, but hearing of Gen. Greene's expected departure, must break his reserve by calling upon him that very day.
    ii, 9
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 15; 2pp.; Painter, Gamaliel, 1742-1819 (Box 5)
    Fishkill - Asking that he bearer, Mr. Ezra Benedict, sergeant in his company of artificers, may get his discharge. Induced by the circumstances of his family to endorse his request. On verso - John Patterson to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 15 - Well aquatinted with the circumstances of Mr. Benedict's family and therefore recommends his discharge, if it can be done without damage to the public.
    ix, 94, 94a
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 January 14; 4pp.; Palfrey, William (Box 5)
    Apologizing for not writing sooner as he has been with his family in the country. Report which prevailed in Boston that Gen. Greene had been kidnapped by the Tories and carried prisoner to New York. has just spent a fortnight with Gen. Hancock, who is sufficiently recovered from his attack of gout to attend the Assembly. Coolness between him and Gen. Gates; neither they nor their ladies visit. Gen. Gates' family involved in quarrels ever since their arrival. Mr. Bob Gates and Mr. Carter fought, but it was a bloodless encounter. Marquis on board the Alliance in Nantasket Road, waiting for a wind. Necessaries of life risen to a terrible pitch. Wishes a "Locke" or "Colbert" might start up and teach the art of finance. Intends to resign his commission, his family being large, his children young and needing his support. Speaks of the accidental shooting of Mr. Andrews. If necessary to appoint some other person as his agent in Boston, begs leave to offer his services. Remembrances to friends. Sends for his amusement the current prices of sundry articles in Boston.
    ii, 12
  - to Gray, George, 1779 January 25; 1p.; Parker, Jeremiah (Box 5)
    Order to shoe the bearer's horse, belonging to Gen. Muhlenberg's brigade. Order to shoe the bearer's wagon horses, belonging to Gen. Muhlenberg's brigade.
    xii, 76, 76a
  - to Gray, George, 1779 February 11; 1p.; Parker, Jeremiah (Box 5)
    Order to have bearer's horses shod immediately.
    xii, 106
  - to Gray, George, 1779 April 3; 1p.; Parker, Richard (Box 5)
    Order to repair the bearer's gun.
    xii, 98
  - to Udny Hay, 1779 November 5; 1p.; Parsell, John and other artificers (Box 5)
    Fishkill - The artificers having met and discussed the offer of $ 10 a day, have decided that it is too little to support themselves and families, and will therefore quit the barracks as soon as a settlement is made.
    ix, 51
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 23; 1p.; Parsons, Samuel Holden, 1737-1789 (Box 5)
    Reading - His brigade ready to march if only they can be supplied with tents and portmanteaus. Enemy's position somewhat altered; their forces chiefly posted at Kingsbrdige, Horn's Hook and near Hallet's Cove, on Long Island; position of their boats. Asks if the late embarkation from New York is not designed for Virginia. Desires to know the situation of Burgoyne's troops.
    v, 67
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 24; 2pp.; Parsons, Samuel Holden, 1737-1789 (Box 5)
    Reading - His brigade totally without portmanteaus or tents. Begs they may be supplied at once. Number of wagons needed.
    vi, 3
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 10; 1p.; Parsons, Samuel Holden, 1737-1789 (Box 5)
    Camp at Smith's Tavern - Complaint by one of the artificers at West Point that the allowance of rum and provisions is insufficient, their labor being exceedingly hard. Asks him to give such orders as he deems necessary.
    vi, 40
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 13; 1p.; Parsons, Samuel Holden, 1737-1789 (Box 5)
    Smith's Tavern - Acknowledging favor of 11th inst. General not willing to let Mr. Jones go. Will us his little influence for Mr. Bushwell. Accounts from Philadelphia of Gen. Lincoln's having defeated the British at South Carolina, 1480 of the enemy said to be killed, wounded and taken prisoners; if true will be a deadly stroke to the British forces.
    vi, 54
  - to unknown correspondent, 1779 December 8; 2pp.; Parsons, Samuel Holden, 1737-1789 (Box 5)